const e="We could not find what you asked for, but got you this",o="civiledu",a=200,i=120,t=[{id:250,question:"When a constitution is difficult to amend it is said to be",option:{a:"rigid",b:"flexible",c:"written",d:"federal"},section:"",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"neco",examyear:"2013"},{id:400,question:"Red-tapism is one the shortcomings of",option:{a:"private enterprise",b:"public service",c:"non-governmental organization",d:"pressure groups"},section:"",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2015"},{id:360,question:"The general attitude of government and society towards cultism is that of",option:{a:"affection",b:"sympathy",c:"abhorrence",d:"support"},section:"",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2016"},{id:138,question:"Traffic lights are also known and referred to as",option:{a:"three directives light",b:"spotlight",c:"flow traffic directive",d:"informative sign"},section:"",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2012"},{id:417,question:"Inter-communal relationship is best described as",option:{a:"the interaction between individuals, groups or organizations with common aspirations",b:"the interaction among individuals and professionals in a social setting",c:"loyalty to community leaders so as to achieve rapid communal development",d:"respect for collective national symbols in order to foster nationalistic feeling"},section:"",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2015"},{id:94,question:"When the national flag is flown half mask, it is a sign of national",option:{a:"centenary celebration",b:"children’s day",c:"independence",d:"mourning"},section:"",image:"",answer:"d",solution:"",examtype:"neco",examyear:"2014"},{id:120,question:"One of the following is a cause of single parents in Nigeria",option:{a:"slow parenting",b:"social group",c:"nature of work",d:"divorce"},section:"",image:"",answer:"d",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2012"},{id:407,question:"Cultism in tertiary institutions in Nigeria was originally introduced to",option:{a:"perpetuate the use of local gin and alcohol",b:"harass opponents of university administrators",c:"fight colonialism and oppressive rules",d:"promote inter-communal marriages."},section:"",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2015"},{id:62,question:"Franchise means right to",option:{a:"contest for political post",b:"join association",c:"live in Nigeria",d:"vote and be voted for"},section:"",image:"",answer:"d",solution:"",examtype:"neco",examyear:"2014"},{id:24,question:"The nearest government to the people and an important means of promoting grassroots development is the",option:{a:"state government",b:"unitary government",c:"local government",d:"federal government"},section:"",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2014"},{id:341,question:"The document containing the aims and programs of a political party is called ...........",option:{a:"register",b:"manifesto",c:"memorandum of party",d:"party library"},section:"",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2011"},{id:113,question:"The following are types of drugs except",option:{a:"cannabis",b:"depressants",c:"benzodiazepine pines",d:"steroids"},section:"",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2012"},{id:313,question:"In Lagos state, the BRT lane is reserved for ....... only",option:{a:"The governor",b:"Soldiers",c:"Commercial buses",d:"BRT buses"},section:"",image:"",answer:"d",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2011"},{id:423,question:"The idea that “Law should be impartial with the people who break it” implies",option:{a:"principle of fair hearing",b:"right to legal representation",c:"equality before the law",d:"prerogative writ of habeas corpus"},section:"",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2015"},{id:211,question:"The process in which every qualified citizen of a state has the right to vote is called ............ suffrage",option:{a:"universal adult",b:"democratic",c:"tax payer",d:"communal"},section:"",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2013"},{id:413,question:"The responsibility of empowering the youth rests mostly with",option:{a:"the political class",b:"religious organizations",c:"university administrators",d:"national government"},section:"One major trend in Kantoga Republic today, especially during elections, is the engagement of youths by some politicians for political thuggery, rigging, stuffing of ballot boxes and other related electoral offences. Most of the youths who are engaged in these crimes have no means of livelihood or are school drop-outs. These youths are Kantoguans who ought to benefit from the enormous wealth and resources of the nation.<br><br>  Unfortunately, this is not the case at the moment. Indeed, it is the duty of government , especially at the centre, to provide entrepreneurial skill acquisition program and start-up funds for small scale businesses to empower the youths. This will reduce the chances of engagement of youths for wrong purposes.",image:"",answer:"d",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2015"},{id:69,question:"Which of the following is a legal obligation of a citizen?",option:{a:"Giving financial assistance to the poor",b:"Helping in community development",c:"Payment of taxes",d:"Respecting the national symbols"},section:"",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"neco",examyear:"2014"},{id:300,question:"Which of the following are Ebola Emergency lines",option:{a:"08023169484 or 08033086660",b:"08023361936 or 08034623521",c:"08023164216 or 08033065936",d:"08055281400 or 08023361936"},section:"",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2011"},{id:352,question:"One of the responsibilities of a good citizen is to",option:{a:"possess an international passport",b:"enjoy all amenities provided by government",c:"serve the country when required",d:"develop his potentialities to the fullest"},section:"",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2016"},{id:253,question:"As Mr Umukoro got to Oghara junction, near Sapele, he packed the bus and bought some roasted monkey bush meat. Some of the passengers in the bus followed suit, that day was a good Friday. On motion Mr Umukoro, the driver and some of the passengers were doing justice to the monkey bush meat. No sooner had they started than they were stopped and Mr Umukoro was fined by men of the FRSC. If the fine was proper which of the reasons bellow could be responsible for it",option:{a:"some of the passengers ate the bush meat while the bus was on motion",b:"Mr Umukoro, the driver was driving and eating at the same time",c:"They were not supposed to eat monkey bush meat because they can contact the Ebola virus from it.",d:"They were not expected to eat and any kind of meat on a good Friday"},section:"",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"neco",examyear:"2013"},{id:13,question:"The National Assembly, Presidency and Court which are inter - related and interdependent in our democracy constitute the",option:{a:"tiers of government",b:"types of democracy",c:"forms of government.",d:"arms of government"},section:"",image:"",answer:"d",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2014"},{id:397,question:"World AIDS day is observed on",option:{a:"20th May",b:"30th July",c:"27th August",d:"1th December"},section:"",image:"",answer:"d",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2015"},{id:220,question:"The farthest government to the people is the ............ government",option:{a:"Local",b:"State",c:"Federal",d:"A and B above"},section:"",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2013"},{id:292,question:"Free, fair and credible elections are attributes of .......",option:{a:"undemocratic government",b:"democratic government",c:"military regime",d:"monarchical governance"},section:"",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"neco",examyear:"2013"},{id:282,question:"Psychopathy is a form of ................ behaviour",option:{a:"Normal",b:"abnormal",c:"desired",d:"valued"},section:"",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"neco",examyear:"2013"},{id:281,question:"Juvenile delinquency refers to",option:{a:"active youths participation in sports",b:"wrong doings by the youths",c:"Refusal to worship God by the youths",d:"Urban Rural migration by the youth"},section:"",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"neco",examyear:"2013"},{id:163,question:"The main objective of pressure groups is to",option:{a:"promote the interest of political parties",b:"influence legislation for the benefit of their member",c:"protect the interest of the country against foreigners",d:"serve as opposition to the government"},section:"",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"neco",examyear:"2012"},{id:131,question:"The organization with the motives and goals of helping people is called",option:{a:"social group",b:"charity group",c:"pressure group",d:"human right group"},section:"",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2012"},{id:227,question:"The system of government in which all aspects of life are controlled by the government is",option:{a:"democracy",b:"totalitarianism",c:"capitalism",d:"socialism"},section:"",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2013"},{id:188,question:"The following are examples of pressure group except",option:{a:"N. U. R. T",b:"NBA",c:"NLC",d:"PDP"},section:"",image:"",answer:"d",solution:"",examtype:"neco",examyear:"2012"},{id:258,question:"In the year 2014, the Nigerian President Good luck Ebelle Jonathan  urged Nigerians to .......... the rumors  that drinking and bathing with salt water prevents or cures Ebola virus",option:{a:"ignore",b:"accept",c:"welcome",d:"embrace"},section:"",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"neco",examyear:"2013"},{id:108,question:"The form of government in which the electorate exercise their governing power directly through their elected 	representation is called ........",option:{a:"supremacy",b:"democracy",c:"autocracy",d:"charismatic"},section:"",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2012"},{id:32,question:"The position of the court on this matter justifies the essence of the",option:{a:"rule of law",b:"legislature",c:"police command",d:"separation of powers"},section:"The Bawali High Court has ordered the police in Area Z Command to produce Mr. Zeb, who is in police custody for an alleged offence. The court insists that Mr. Zeb cannot be punished until he is found guilty of breach of any law of the land by a court of competent jurisdiction.",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2014"},{id:265,question:"Some years ago a popular Governor in one of the states in Nigeria was asked to mention some mineral 	resources from his state. He made mention of “Fanta, Pepsi, Coca cola. The governor is",option:{a:"right",b:"wrong",c:"illiterate",d:"unpatriotic"},section:"",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"neco",examyear:"2013"},{id:206,question:"The process of enlightening or training citizens on their rights and responsibilities is known as",option:{a:"Workshop training",b:"Citizenship Education",c:"Political Education",d:"Citizenship Rights"},section:"",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2013"},{id:252,question:"Ejiro, who is not sick decide to take the same drug for the same duration as recommended for Omonigho by the doctor.Ejiro’s action can be described as a form of",option:{a:"preventive measure",b:"drug abuse",c:"drug trafficking",d:"Self help activity"},section:"",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"neco",examyear:"2013"},{id:89,question:"One of the major problems facing local government administration in Nigeria is",option:{a:"insufficient councilors",b:"lack of control by the central government",c:"lack of funds",d:"leadership"},section:"",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"neco",examyear:"2014"},{id:428,question:"Which of the following is a major challenge to civil society in Nigeria?",option:{a:"Value disorientation",b:"Diverse political interests",c:"Inadequate funding",d:"Unstable political system"},section:"",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2015"},{id:205,question:"Nigeria became independent in ........... and a Republic in ................ Respectively",option:{a:"1963 and 1960",b:"1960 and 1963",c:"1954 and 1960",d:"None of the above"},section:"",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2013"},{id:197,question:".............. was the capital of Nigeria before .................",option:{a:"Abuja - Lagos",b:"Lagos - Abuja",c:"Ikeja - Abuja",d:"Benin - Abuja"},section:"",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2013"},{id:283,question:"Consumers of ......... especially ........... and ..............stand the a great risk of contacting the Ebola disease",option:{a:"fish, tilapia, titus",b:"bush meat, monkey, bat",c:"meat, cow, dog",d:"vegetable, water leaf, bitter leaf"},section:"",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"neco",examyear:"2013"},{id:80,question:"A de-facto authority is mostly associated with",option:{a:"anarchy.",b:"customs and tradition.",c:"force.",d:"law."},section:"",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"neco",examyear:"2014"},{id:325,question:"A committee of PDP members is made up of 9 Hausas, 8 Igbo and 7 Yorubas. If the president wishes to choose just one person to be his special adviser, find the probability that the person chosen is neither Hausa nor Yoruba",option:{a:"7/24",b:"2/3",c:"3/8",d:"1/3"},section:"",image:"",answer:"d",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2011"},{id:431,question:"Justice demands that people should always do what is",option:{a:"persistently convenient",b:"consistently right",c:"individually acceptable",d:"courageously necessary"},section:"",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2015"},{id:139,question:"One of the following is not a federal road agencies",option:{a:"DTO",b:"FRSC",c:"TRACE",d:"VIO"},section:"",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2012"},{id:356,question:"Which of the following statements is not correct?",option:{a:"Valid driver’s license must be obtained before attempting to drive",b:"Flowing garment can be worn on a motorcycle or bicycle",c:"Headlights should be used during unfavourable weather",d:"Drivers must not engage in distractive activities while driving"},section:"",image:"",answer:"d",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2016"},{id:379,question:"The motherland in the monologue could best be described as",option:{a:"a nation in transition",b:"a morally upgrading country",c:"a socially viable nation",d:"an ethically bankrupt country"},section:"Oh Motherland, you were a precious country, a beacon of hope and aspiration as well as toga of pride of your citizens at independence. However, today you are bedeviled with evil, engulfed in darkness and to say the obvious, at the edge of total moral collapse. Corruption, fraud, deception and dishonesty are prevalent; drug peddlers are having a field day. In schools and colleges, radicalism, prostitution, cultism, examination malpractice among other social vices are order of the day.",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2016"},{id:195,question:"Austerity measure was first introduced in Nigeria by ..........",option:{a:"President Babangida",b:"Olusegun Obasanjo",c:"President Sehu Shagari",d:"President Goodluck Jonathan"},section:"",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"neco",examyear:"2012"},{id:246,question:"Juvenile delinquency and cultism are ......... and should be .........",option:{a:"undesirable - encouraged",b:"desirable - discouraged",c:"undesirable - discouraged",d:"desirable - discouraged"},section:"",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"neco",examyear:"2013"},{id:426,question:"A major civil society group which campaigned against military rule prior to the advent of the Fourth Republic in Nigeria is the",option:{a:"Campaign for Democracy",b:"Save Nigeria Group",c:"Civil Liberties Organization",d:"National Democratic Coalition"},section:"",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2015"},{id:278,question:"Which of the following is not the civic obligation of a citizen",option:{a:"payment of taxes",b:"freedom of conscience and speech",c:"voting during elections",d:"obedience to law"},section:"",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"neco",examyear:"2013"},{id:130,question:"One of the following is a social group",option:{a:"dangote group of companies",b:"rotary club",c:"Millan group",d:"human right Africa"},section:"",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2012"},{id:182,question:"A manifesto refers to",option:{a:"the register of party members",b:"rejected ballot papers",c:"valid ballot papers",d:"Document containing the aims and programmes of   a political party"},section:"",image:"",answer:"d",solution:"",examtype:"neco",examyear:"2012"},{id:338,question:"On the 18th of November 2014 in Yobe, some crowds lynched a suspected suicide bomber. The action of the crowd is .....",option:{a:"right because ‘he who kills by the sword must die by the sword’",b:"wrong because they have unlawfully taken the law into their hands, they should have handed the suicide  bomber over to the police",c:"right because we all have to fights against all forms of terrorism",d:"right so that others will learn lesson from this action"},section:"",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2011"},{id:275,question:"If the crowd insisted on keeping their distance what appropriate action could they have taken",option:{a:"call the appropriate health department to intervene",b:"left him to his fate",c:"stone him to death",d:"desert him"},section:"A certain man came to visit his friend at Shomolu one early morning. Unexpectedly the man fainted and slumped. He lay on the floor for several hours and looking lifeless. The crowd and even the friend he came to visit kept a reasonable distance from him. No one came to his rescue or even attempted to touch him. As luck would have it he regained his strength after about five hours and managed to go back to his house",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"neco",examyear:"2013"},{id:366,question:"Which of the following is not a means of reducing the incidence of HIV/AIDS in our society?",option:{a:"Education and enlightenment programs",b:"The use of specially designed cutlery by victims",c:"Avoiding pre-marital and extra-marital sex",d:"Upholding the value of chastity"},section:"",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2016"},{id:385,question:"According to the above story, the open trial of Dr. Fajir and his representation by lawyers of his choice in a court of competent jurisdiction is an indication of",option:{a:"respect for habeas corpus",b:"freedom of expression",c:"respect for human rights",d:"freedom of legal representation"},section:"Dr. Fajir was the Minister of Works and Urban Development in the Gambia Republic. As such, he was entrusted with the public fund so that his ministry could construct new roads and rehabilitate the existing ones. Unfortunately. Dr Fajir embezzled the money entrusted in his care and siphoned same to his foreign accounts. This led to the deplorable conditions of roads in the Republic. The Crime Commission arrested and prosecuted him accordingly. Subsequently, he was given the opportunity to be defended by lawyers of his choice in a Court of Law. However, he was found guilty and sentenced to 15 years imprisonment with hard labour without the option of a fine. In addition, he forfeited all his ill-gotten wealth to the Republic.",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2016"},{id:271,question:"Mr Dickson’s little son, clement was sent away from school because he has not paid his school fees of 	N=11,000. That same day as Mr Dickson boarded a Danfo bus he noticed that the purse of a fellow passenger dropped on the floor of the bus. Mr Dickson tactically picked up the purse, opened it and saw a handsome sum of N=100,000. No body in the bus noticed him, neither did the fellow passenger. As a patriotic and good citizen of Nigeria, what is Mr Dickson expected to do",option:{a:"Pay his tithe (1/10 of the money) to the church take the rest and pray for forgiveness",b:"Draw the attention of the fellow passenger and give the money back to him /her",c:"Use part of the money to pay his son’s fess and keep the rest because opportunity comes but once",d:"Leave the purse on the floor, and mind his business"},section:"",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"neco",examyear:"2013"},{id:357,question:"Cultism can best be discouraged through",option:{a:"mentoring of cultists by the rich",b:"provision of jobs for cultists",c:"sensitization on the dangers of cultism",d:"establishment of cultists support groups"},section:"",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2016"},{id:391,question:"In which year did the United Nations General Assembly adopt the Universal Declaration of Human Rights?",option:{a:"1945",b:"1946",c:"1947",d:"1948"},section:"",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2015"},{id:178,question:"All type of government perform all the following functions except",option:{a:"providing welfare and developmental facilities",b:"maintaining law and order",c:"encouraging the struggle for power",d:"encouraging trade with other state"},section:"",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"neco",examyear:"2012"},{id:14,question:"A system of government that listens to public opinion and tolerates opposition is",option:{a:"dictatorial regime",b:"capitalist regime",c:"democratic regime",d:"socialist regime"},section:"",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2014"},{id:348,question:"Lack of interest in politics by citizens in the country is referred to as political",option:{a:"ignorance",b:"apathy",c:"participation",d:"socialization"},section:"",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2016"},{id:399,question:"In order to avoid undue interference in the process of governance, there should be",option:{a:"clear cut separation of governmental powers",b:"proper fusion of governmental powers and functions",c:"more roles for traditional rulers in the governmental process",d:"additional responsibility for local government council"},section:"",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2015"},{id:376,question:"One of the major complaints against public service is",option:{a:"inefficiency",b:"understaffing",c:"victimization",d:"discrimination"},section:"",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2016"},{id:351,question:"“We the people of the Federal Republic of Nigeria” is usually the opening phrase of the preamble to",option:{a:"coup announcement",b:"government gazettes",c:"constitution",d:"mansard"},section:"",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2016"},{id:170,question:"Which of these countries operate a unitary system of 	government",option:{a:"Nigeria",b:"U. S. A",c:"Ghana",d:"Britain"},section:"",image:"",answer:"d",solution:"",examtype:"neco",examyear:"2012"},{id:125,question:"The following are causes of emergency rule except",option:{a:"crisis",b:"blood lettings",c:"stage peaceful protest",d:"sabotage / terrorism"},section:"",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2012"},{id:33,question:"Leaders can best protect the interests of their followers by",option:{a:"embarking on periodic constitutional review",b:"creating socio - economic opportunities for foreigners",c:"creating conducive atmosphere for participation",d:"rewarding supporters with contracts"},section:"",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2014"},{id:367,question:"Youth empowerment promotes",option:{a:"self-reliance",b:"youthful exuberance",c:"pursuit of higher education",d:"foreign scholarship"},section:"",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2016"},{id:136,question:"The process whereby an individual choose to favour a person who come from his family or tribe over other people or tribes is known as",option:{a:"stereotype",b:"ethnicity",c:"nepotism",d:"favouritism"},section:"",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2012"},{id:294,question:"Public service belongs to ................",option:{a:"the legislative arm of government",b:"the judiciary arm of government",c:"senate arm of government",d:"the executive arm of government"},section:"",image:"",answer:"d",solution:"",examtype:"neco",examyear:"2013"},{id:432,question:"Orderliness in the society is good mainly because it",option:{a:"discourages poverty",b:"promotes peace and stability",c:"guarantees employment for youths",d:"ensures maximum rewards from leaders"},section:"",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2015"},{id:58,question:"One of the aims of citizenship education is to produce students with",option:{a:"creative skill.",b:"high sense of entrepreneurial skill.",c:"high sense of patriotism.",d:"manipulative skills."},section:"",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"neco",examyear:"2014"},{id:126,question:"The World AIDs Day is usually ..........................",option:{a:"June 12th every year",b:"May second every year",c:"October 1st every year",d:"December 1st every year"},section:"",image:"",answer:"d",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2012"},{id:365,question:"Drug law enforcement agencies in Nigeria are not empowered to",option:{a:"execute drug suspects",b:"arrest drug barons",c:"prosecute drug traffickers",d:"rehabilitate drug addicts"},section:"",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2016"},{id:156,question:"Workers in the Public Corporations are known as",option:{a:"Civil servants",b:"Private employees",c:"Public servants",d:"Professional employees"},section:"",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"neco",examyear:"2012"},{id:35,question:"Civil societies are vital for the promotion of popular participation because they are",option:{a:"profit - oriented organizations",b:"engaged in developmental programmes",c:"involved in political education",d:"formidable oppositions to government"},section:"",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2014"},{id:288,question:"Through which of these can citizenship status be acquired",option:{a:"birth, naturalization, honorary and registration",b:"birth, colonization and integration",c:"referendum, incorporation and acceptance",d:"convention registration and colonization"},section:"",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"neco",examyear:"2013"},{id:114,question:"Cocaine, morphine and heroin are example of",option:{a:"tobacco",b:"steroids",c:"narcotics",d:"inhalants"},section:"",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2012"},{id:25,question:"Democratic governance is usually characterized by",option:{a:"free, fair and credible elections",b:"buoyant and competitive economy",c:"accessible employment opportunities",d:"youth participation in governance"},section:"",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2014"},{id:381,question:"Based on the monologue above, the best approach to curb moral decadence in the motherland is by",option:{a:"value re-orientation",b:"introducing war against corruption",c:"legalizing capital punishment",d:"sending corrupt officials on exile"},section:"Oh Motherland, you were a precious country, a beacon of hope and aspiration as well as toga of pride of your citizens at independence. However, today you are bedeviled with evil, engulfed in darkness and to say the obvious, at the edge of total moral collapse. Corruption, fraud, deception and dishonesty are prevalent; drug peddlers are having a field day. In schools and colleges, radicalism, prostitution, cultism, examination malpractice among other social vices are order of the day.",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2016"},{id:207,question:"The ideas, things or principles cherished by the people in a community are referred to as",option:{a:"rights",b:"culture",c:"values",d:"due process"},section:"",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2013"},{id:219,question:"The use of illicit or hard drugs such as marijuana (Indian hemp) heroine, morphine etc. is known as",option:{a:"Human right abuse",b:"Drug trafficking",c:"Drug enhancement",d:"Drug abuse"},section:"",image:"",answer:"d",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2013"},{id:434,question:"Ade’s action as shown in the dialogue is a demonstration of political",option:{a:"wisdom",b:"apathy",c:"lawlessness",d:"participation"},section:"<strong>Zubar: </strong> Today is the day for gubernatorial elections, Ade what are you waiting for? Let us go and cast our votes for candidates of our choice<br><br> 	<strong>Ade: </strong> I have no interest in an election which not yield any dividend of democracy. Our political elite are only concerned about their interest when they get to the position 	of authority. For crying out loud, I have made up my mind that l will not vote again. <br><br> 	<strong>Zubar: </strong> Haba! Ade, don’t you remember Abraham Lincoln’s words that ‘all men are not just, all men are not true. But ...... for every scoundrel there is a hero, that for every selfish politician, there is a dedicated leader!’ Come on, go and cast your vote so that we can choose the right person for the position and change the political, economic and social directions of our great state.",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2015"},{id:310,question:"If six political parties contest for an election (A, B, C, D, E, F), what is the probability that party C will wine the election",option:{a:"1/3",b:"1/4",c:"1/6",d:"1/2"},section:"",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2011"},{id:91,question:"The headquarters of ECOWAS is located in",option:{a:"Abuja",b:"Accra",c:"Adis-Ababa",d:"Lome"},section:"",image:"",answer:"d",solution:"",examtype:"neco",examyear:"2014"},{id:53,question:"The responsibilities of government to   its citizens include the following, except",option:{a:"creating employment opportunity",b:"maintenance of law and order",c:"payment of property tax to its citizens",d:"protection of lives and property"},section:"",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"neco",examyear:"2014"},{id:83,question:"One of the civic responsibilities of a citizen is to obey",option:{a:"bye-laws.",b:"constituted authority.",c:"court judgments.",d:"edicts."},section:"",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"neco",examyear:"2014"},{id:436,question:"From the above dialogue, political leaders can encourage citizens to perform their civic duties by",option:{a:"fulfilling their electoral promises",b:"travelling overseas to seek for foreign investors",c:"engaging in religious activities",d:"visiting all the local governments in the country"},section:"<strong>Zubar: </strong> Today is the day for gubernatorial elections, Ade what are you waiting for? Let us go and cast our votes for candidates of our choice<br><br> 	<strong>Ade: </strong> I have no interest in an election which not yield any dividend of democracy. Our political elite are only concerned about their interest when they get to the position 	of authority. For crying out loud, I have made up my mind that l will not vote again. <br><br> 	<strong>Zubar: </strong> Haba! Ade, don’t you remember Abraham Lincoln’s words that ‘all men are not just, all men are not true. But ...... for every scoundrel there is a hero, that for every selfish politician, there is a dedicated leader!’ Come on, go and cast your vote so that we can choose the right person for the position and change the political, economic and social directions of our great state.",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2015"},{id:124,question:"All the following can limit the right of a citizen except",option:{a:"war",b:"state of emergency",c:"universality",d:"military rule"},section:"",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2012"},{id:28,question:"One of the conditions which can limit the enjoyment of Human Rights in Nigeria is the",option:{a:"acceptance of foreign aid by the government",b:"improvement in literacy level of the citizens",c:"declaration of state of emergency by government",d:"periodic review of the constitution by government"},section:"",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2014"},{id:67,question:"The right of an individual to seek redress in a law court is categorized under",option:{a:"economic.",b:"political",c:"procedural,",d:"social"},section:"",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"neco",examyear:"2014"},{id:173,question:"In a democratic government, political sovereignty is vested in the",option:{a:"legislature",b:"elite",c:"executive",d:"electorate"},section:"",image:"",answer:"d",solution:"",examtype:"neco",examyear:"2012"},{id:160,question:"The office responsible for announcing the result of an election is known as",option:{a:"ballot officer",b:"presiding officer",c:"Returning officer",d:"Electoral officer"},section:"",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"neco",examyear:"2012"},{id:244,question:"The president belongs to .......... arm of the government",option:{a:"Legislative",b:"Judiciary",c:"Executive",d:"Anti-crime"},section:"",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2013"},{id:276,question:"If the crowd suspected that he had the Ebola virus and wish to call the Ebola emergency line, which one of the following could they have called?",option:{a:"08023169485",b:"0803361424",c:"08023361936",d:"08027063614"},section:"A certain man came to visit his friend at Shomolu one early morning. Unexpectedly the man fainted and slumped. He lay on the floor for several hours and looking lifeless. The crowd and even the friend he came to visit kept a reasonable distance from him. No one came to his rescue or even attempted to touch him. As luck would have it he regained his strength after about five hours and managed to go back to his house",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"neco",examyear:"2013"},{id:412,question:"From the above write-up what category of Kantoguan youth deserves to be effectively empowered?",option:{a:"Children of the ruling political class",b:"Unemployed youths and school drop-outs",c:"University undergraduates",d:"Youth wing of religious organizations"},section:"One major trend in Kantoga Republic today, especially during elections, is the engagement of youths by some politicians for political thuggery, rigging, stuffing of ballot boxes and other related electoral offences. Most of the youths who are engaged in these crimes have no means of livelihood or are school drop-outs. These youths are Kantoguans who ought to benefit from the enormous wealth and resources of the nation.<br><br>  Unfortunately, this is not the case at the moment. Indeed, it is the duty of government , especially at the centre, to provide entrepreneurial skill acquisition program and start-up funds for small scale businesses to empower the youths. This will reduce the chances of engagement of youths for wrong purposes.",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2015"},{id:323,question:"Naira and Kobo was introduced in Nigeria in ..............",option:{a:"2nd July,1963",b:"1st January 1972",c:"June 12, 1993",d:"March13, 1995"},section:"",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2011"},{id:101,question:"............ is obtained from the Nigerian immigration services as a requirement to travel out of the country",option:{a:"ticket",b:"yellow card",c:"passport",d:"national ID card"},section:"",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2012"},{id:343,question:"Orderliness can be defined as",option:{a:"being punctual to work",b:"studying diligently in school",c:"doing things in a proper way",d:"learning the Western way of life"},section:"",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2016"},{id:215,question:"Which of the following can cause Human Trafficking in a country",option:{a:"poverty, youth unemployment and greed",b:"Sound education and proper counselling",c:"Social and economic contentment",d:"B and C above"},section:"",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2013"},{id:119,question:"........ is the type of parenthood where a different couple raise a particular child that is not their own",option:{a:"helicopter parent",b:"foster parenthood",c:"slow parenting",d:"different parenthood"},section:"",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2012"},{id:264,question:"For now the Ebola disease has",option:{a:"no known cure",b:"several known cures",c:"cannot kill its action",d:"no physically observable symptoms"},section:"",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"neco",examyear:"2013"},{id:105,question:"Newspapers and magazine and example of ..... media",option:{a:"print",b:"electronic",c:"advertising",d:"mass"},section:"",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2012"},{id:168,question:"Custom refers to .............",option:{a:"tradition or social value or patterns",b:"image of a country",c:"sharing similar or common ethnic background",d:"A state of feeling of oneness among the people"},section:"",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"neco",examyear:"2012"},{id:398,question:"An enabling environment created to help an individual have effective control of his/her situation is known as",option:{a:"reinforcement",b:"empowerment",c:"endowment",d:"enhancement"},section:"",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2015"},{id:404,question:"A responsible parent is someone who",option:{a:"cares and provides for the children",b:"indulges the children because of love",c:"works in order to receive salary",d:"employs house-helps to take care of the children"},section:"",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2015"},{id:312,question:"In Lagos state and some other states in Nigeria, motorcycle (okada) riders are expected to wear ............ while on motion",option:{a:"Boot",b:"Hand glove",c:"Crash helmet",d:"Black coloured shirt"},section:"",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2011"},{id:176,question:"The private ownership of the means of production is a feature of",option:{a:"capitalism",b:"Socialism",c:"Communalism",d:"Communism"},section:"",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"neco",examyear:"2012"},{id:291,question:"It is often said that public servants cannot be held responsible for their actions. This principle denotes .................",option:{a:"anonymity",b:"civic irresponsibility",c:"accountability",d:"neutrality"},section:"",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"neco",examyear:"2013"},{id:305,question:"A sense of right and wrong guiding a person’s action is known as",option:{a:"attitude",b:"conscience",c:"action",d:"manner"},section:"",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2011"},{id:268,question:"Political Apathy can lead to",option:{a:"very fast pace of development",b:"the emergence of sound democratic government",c:"wrong set of people coming into power",d:"development of sound political culture"},section:"",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"neco",examyear:"2013"},{id:267,question:"The right practice of democracy can",option:{a:"ensure equity, justice and far play",b:"discourage political education and awareness’",c:"political unrest",d:"lawlessness"},section:"",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"neco",examyear:"2013"},{id:420,question:"Effective and responsible parenthood is primarily",option:{a:"a national duty",b:"a military duty",c:"a political duty",d:"an economic duty"},section:"",image:"",answer:"a",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2015"},{id:121,question:".......... strengthens the sensitive mental and emotional bond between the parent and children",option:{a:"narcissistic parenting",b:"attachment parenting",c:"positive parenting",d:"teenage parenting"},section:"",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2012"},{id:196,question:"Before crossing the road you are expected to ...........",option:{a:"Look left and then right",b:"Look left, right and left again",c:"Look back and left",d:"Look forward for oncoming okada"},section:"",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2013"},{id:257,question:"Plenty of money in the society, not backed by commensurate productive activities can lead to",option:{a:"deflation",b:"inflation",c:"National developmental",d:"cashless society"},section:"",image:"",answer:"b",solution:"",examtype:"neco",examyear:"2013"},{id:328,question:"The full meaning of NYSC is ..............",option:{a:"Now Your Suffering Continues",b:"Nigeria Youths Serving Christ",c:"National Youth Service Corps",d:"Nigerian Youth Service Corps"},section:"",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2011"},{id:36,question:"From this dialogue, it is very likely that Wanja will be exhibiting the following characters except",option:{a:"disobedience to constituted authority",b:"truancy and perpetual lateness to school",c:"hospitable attitude towards people",d:"arrogance and unruly behaviour."},section:"Ada:      Wanja, where are you going to in this ungodly hour of the night? <br> 	Wanja:   I am heading towards my usual joint to enjoy myself <br>	 	Ada:       Which joint?<br> 	Wanja:   XYZ. Night Club, where I take marijuana and alcoholic beverages. I really want to be high 			      tonight so that when people see me tomorrow, they will fear and respect me.<br> 	Ada:     Remember, people who work under the influence of hard drugs and alcoholic beverages are prone to either psychiatric problems or premature death. Softly young man, imbibe good - natured character, you have the world at your feet and a destiny to fulfil. Pray you will not be the architect of your own misfortune.",image:"",answer:"c",solution:"",examtype:"wassce",examyear:"2014"}],n={message:e,subject:o,status:200,total:120,data:t};export{t as data,n as default,e as message,a as status,o as subject,i as total};
